<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Josh Crain Notes</title>
  <subtitle>I am an experienced web designer, product designer, and front-end developer. Design allows me to make an impact through user advocacy, research, web standards, and code.</subtitle>
  <link href="https://joshcrain.io/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://joshcrain.io/"/>
  <updated>2018-11-21T18:00:00-06:00</updated>
  <id>https://joshcrain.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Josh Crain</name>
    <email>josh.crain+io.gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The First Weeks of October</title>
    <link href="https://joshcrain.io/notes/2020/first-weeks-october/"/>
    <updated>2020-10-30T19:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://joshcrain.io/notes/2020/first-weeks-october/</id>
    <content type="html"><h2>I.</h2>
<p>buoyed mounds of mist <br>
drift under the silent dome <br>
slowly asunder</p>
<h2>II.</h2>
<p>night answers her kin<br>
with a stillness bathed in blue<br>
abiding till dawn</p>
<h2>III.</h2>
<p>gilded bough and blade<br>
point west to the autumn blaze<br>
higher now the rays</p>
<h2>IV.</h2>
<p>a flit and flicker <br>
hops through willow and wicker <br>
weaving threads of light</p>
<h2>V.</h2>
<p>the maple crimsons <br>
then sheds her resplendent robe <br>
for a winter rest</p>
<h2>VI.</h2>
<p>shadows move beyond<br>
the face—knows and examines<br>
the passing season</p>
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Crain Family Ancestry</title>
    <link href="https://joshcrain.io/notes/2020/crain-family-ancestry/"/>
    <updated>2020-08-06T19:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://joshcrain.io/notes/2020/crain-family-ancestry/</id>
    <content type="html"><p><span class="dropcap">M</span>y dad began work on a family history at a time when the only way to do so by letter correspondence. He made inquiries off and on for years until health issues prevented him from doing more. Years passed and much of his work became lost through a variety of circumstances. I remember a phone conversation with him where he was particularly lucid. He expressed the devastation he felt at the loss of all the work. It was during that conversation I decided to help with his project.</p>
<p>To get started I opened a free trial account on ancestry.com. This helped me identify a list of names and dates and establish a family tree. Right away I had more generations, branches, and names than I had expected. I was unsure if what I had found was accurate, it seemed too good to be true. I began to cross-reference names and dates using a variety of web searches. I rediscovered the <a href="http://www.archive.org/">Internet Archive</a> which is where I found most of the sources. It was the first two books, <em>Genealogy Of The Crane Family, Volumes I &amp; II</em>, by Ellery Bicknell Crane proved to be the most valuable. They trace the family lineage to two brothers, Benjamin and Henry. Both lived in the Connecticut Colony as early as 1655.</p>
<p>It is my understanding the United States centennial prompted a renewed interest in the foundation of the country. Families known to be in the country for some time commissioned books as a way to claim their participation in the founding of the country. For a year I traced down as many other <a href="https://joshcrain.io/ancestry/sources/">sources</a> as I could and the sketch of my family history began to take shape. The results of my research wouldn’t have been possible without the aid of these public domain books.</p>
<p>When I learned one of my ancestors was involved in the Revolutionary War I wanted to visit some of those locations. In the fall of 2015 I visited the <a href="https://www.nps.gov/sara/index.htm">Saratoga Battlefield</a>, <a href="https://www.fortticonderoga.org/">Fort Ticonderoga</a>, and <a href="https://historicsites.vermont.gov/mount-independence">Mount Independence</a> on a trip from Buffalo to New Hampshire.</p>
<p>It was after the visit to Saratoga I made contact with a park ranger and historian. He set me straight on some details of my ancestors’s military service. Others have reached out after visiting the website and have offered assistance. One individual shared a 40 page pension document for the revolutionary war.</p>
<p>There were surprises along the way. The spelling of our name changed from <em>Crane</em> to <em>Crain</em> around 1863. The headstones of a husband and wife stand side-by-side with different spellings of the same last name. The reason is unknown, but likely the family (or the headstone carver) was illiterate. The spelling change had been an obstacle for my dad. Who would expect the spelling of a man’s name would happen so late in life?</p>
<p>There were many impactful moments during this project. During my research I gained a new appreciation for the history and found great enjoyment in the work. The <a href="https://joshcrain.io/ancestry/">Crain Ancestry</a> project began a way to for me to help my dad and restore what he had lost. The realization of how easily history, even family history, can be lost or forgotten. Papers can be misplaced, but how could names be <em>forgotten</em> after four or five generations? These were people whose lives led to my life, who were completely unknown to my father and grandfather. The fragility of <em>this</em> history was a reminder of how important it is to preserve  our past.</p>
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The launch of this website</title>
    <link href="https://joshcrain.io/notes/2020/website-launch/"/>
    <updated>2020-07-26T19:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://joshcrain.io/notes/2020/website-launch/</id>
    <content type="html"><p><span class="dropcap">W</span>hen I began work on this site more than a year ago my goal was to  build something other than a web designer’s personal website. I’ll start  off by saying I failed at that. I had ideas, grand in their understatement, that led to struggles and then indecision. Those  struggles made way for what was natural—a web designer’s  website, because of course, that’s my job.</p>
<p>The site would need to be fast, inclusive, easy to manage, with  minimal friction to deploy. I did not want to spend all my time  tinkering and never get around to the content. Simplicity  would be of the upmost importance and would be my guiding principle.  This goal was successful and has allowed me to focus on <em>some</em> content  and learning new things. I have allowed the process to be slow and  ongoing. Even in small bursts I have learned a lot and have had a chance  to experiment. These skills have translated to the real world where  I’ve added build tools to my workflow. The focus and work for this site  has been different than I had hoped for but valuable none-the-less.</p>
<p>Although I’ve had personal and portfolio sites in the past I was  ready to begin anew. Over the last several years I lost interest in all the work. It was no longer attractive to have the limitations of someone else’s platform, all for the sake of maintaining <em>my personal brand</em>. All that to say—it’s been a few years. Much of the content I have to draw from is not the direction of this site (<em>not very good</em>). Limited content has lent itself to a slow, evolving design process.</p>
<p>I keep <a href="https://joshcrain.io/tags/weeknotes/">weeknotes</a> most weeks, publishing what I write on my phone during the moments between things. It’s all I can do some months and that’s better than nothing. It has also been an interesting exercise during the pandemic.</p>
<p>The domain name, <a href="https://joshcrain.io/">joshcrain.io</a>, is a new one. Another, more <em>common</em> domain, has remained unavailable for years. I chose use <a href="https://www.11ty.dev/">Eleventy</a> for publishing because of it’s simplicity. The documentation was not complicated and well written with helpful examples. <a href="https://www.filamentgroup.com/lab/build-a-blog/" rel="noopener">An article</a> from Filament Group got me started. The initial build took a few hours and I was up and running.</p>
<p>Though the site went live on January 15, 2020, I’ve avoided any sort  of acknowledgment of it existence. There is still plenty to do. Much  left unfinished. I may never get to where it’s done, so why wait.  It’s live.</p>
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Becoming a front-end master</title>
    <link href="https://joshcrain.io/notes/2020/becoming-a-front-end-master/"/>
    <updated>2020-03-15T19:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://joshcrain.io/notes/2020/becoming-a-front-end-master/</id>
    <content type="html"><p><span class="dropcap">R</span>ecently, I encountered <a href="https://css-tricks.com/become-a-front-end-master-in-2020-with-these-10-project-ideas/">an article</a> last November from Chris Coyer which was very helpful. This last year has been really rough for a number of reasons. I haven’t felt like myself, much less a <em>front-end master</em>. Chris’ article prompted me to explore some new things in the free moments I have and practice my skills in small but meaningful ways. In the following weeks and months I followed the recommendations—and I’ve learned a lot.</p>
<h2>Try out a static site generator</h2>
<p>Check. This site uses <a href="https://www.11ty.io/">Eleventy</a> for static site generation. Changes are tracked with Git and pushed to <a href="https://github.com/joshcrain/eleventy-intro">a Github repo</a> using command line. The site is deployed automatically by Netlify using <a href="https://docs.netlify.com/site-deploys/create-deploys/#deploy-with-git">continuous deployment</a>.</p>
<h2>Read a bit about Serverless</h2>
<p>This <em>was</em> an area where needed to do some <a href="https://serverless.css-tricks.com/about/">reading</a>. With so many <a href="https://serverless.css-tricks.com/services/major">services</a> out there, there’s a lot to follow. Often the best way to get started is to build something. The next challenge was helpful.</p>
<h2>Build a beautiful form in HTML/CSS</h2>
<p>I spent some time to learn <a href="https://css-tricks.com/form-validation-part-1-constraint-validation-html/">all about form validation</a> and see how much can be done in just HTML, then HTML <em>plus</em> some CSS, then with some vanilla JavaScript. I cannot get over how easy it was to implement a form with <a href="https://docs.netlify.com/forms/setup/">Netlify forms</a>. Take a look and <a href="https://joshcrain.io/say-hello/">say hello</a>.</p>
<h2>Install the Axe accessibility plugin for DevTools</h2>
<h3>Landmarks must have an accessible name</h3>
<p>Landmarks (i.e. <code>&lt;main&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;header&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;nav&gt;</code>, etc.) need to have a unique role or label. In addition, it was also a good time to review <a href="https://css-tricks.com/how-to-section-your-html/">how to section your HTML</a> (I had an <code>&lt;aside&gt;</code> inside the <code>&lt;article&gt;</code>).</p>
<h3>Alternative text should not be repeated as text</h3>
<p>This can be a more annoying one to achieve when working with a CMS or templated build. Especially when the image is used as navigation. It’s easy to just reuse the label for the page name instead of a creating a new value for the ALT attribute.</p>
<h2>Spin up a copy of Fractal</h2>
<p>This <em>has</em> helped me think about how I would build a front-end as components. Fractal isn’t tied to a specific framework, which I really like. I have experimented with React and ... for this purpose in my day job, but I’m not ready make a decision. Fractal gives me a chance to build and document a strategy ahead of time without any commitment.</p>
<p>It was helpful to see how others have structured their Pattern Libraries in Fractal.  <a href="http://patterns.perchcms.com/">Perch Pattern Library</a> and <a href="http://bits.24ways.org/">Bits for 24 Ways</a> are a few good examples.</p>
<h2>Implement an SVG icon system</h2>
<p>Icon fonts are so easy to implement, but also have <a href="https://css-tricks.com/icon-fonts-vs-svg/">some negatives</a>. Inline SVGs are a great approach especially if the icons are used in the build template. Chris’ book, <a href="https://abookapart.com/products/practical-svg">Practical SVG</a> introduced me to a lot more than I knew existed about SVG for web.</p>
<p>This site is all about simplicity so it uses in-lined SVG—<a href="https://css-tricks.com/pretty-good-svg-icon-system/">a pretty good icon system</a>. For the larger application I work on, <a href="https://css-tricks.com/creating-svg-icon-system-react/">maybe something like this</a>. For a large application, icon fonts are still somewhat appealing because of the ease of caching.</p>
<h2>Implement a service worker</h2>
<p>Read <a href="https://abookapart.com/products/going-offline">a book about them</a>. Do something  <a href="https://simpleoffline.website/">very small</a>. Check out  <a href="https://developers.google.com/web/tools/workbox">a framework</a> centered around them. Service workers install the front-end of <em>this site</em> directly on your device after the first visit. In practice, a service worker can offer great performance benefits that go beyond traditional caching.</p>
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Love Bears All Things</title>
    <link href="https://joshcrain.io/notes/2020/love-bears-all-things/"/>
    <updated>2020-02-13T18:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>https://joshcrain.io/notes/2020/love-bears-all-things/</id>
    <content type="html"><p>A year ago for Valentine’s Day I made a couple bears in love. Illustration in CSS and HTML is completely unnecessary—but fun!</p>
<figure>
<p class="codepen" data-height="687" data-theme-id="light" data-default-tab="result" data-user="joshcrain" data-slug-hash="yGZBGr" style="height: 687px; box-sizing: border-box; display: flex; align-items: center; justify-content: center; border: 2px solid; margin: 1em 0; padding: 1em;" data-pen-title="Love Bears All Things - CSS Illustration">
  <span>See the Pen <a href="https://codepen.io/joshcrain/pen/yGZBGr/">
  Love Bears All Things - CSS Illustration</a> by Josh Crain (<a href="https://codepen.io/joshcrain">@joshcrain</a>)
  on <a href="https://codepen.io/">CodePen</a>.</span>
</p>
<script async="" src="https://static.codepen.io/assets/embed/ei.js"></script>
<figcaption>Originally posted on <a href="https://twitter.com/thejoshcrain/status/1096067158512152582" rel="noopener">Twitter</a>. Edit 1/21/2020: Something has happened to their arms in Chrome! Still good in Safari and FF. </figcaption>
</figure> </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Yamaha SHS-10</title>
    <link href="https://joshcrain.io/notes/2020/yamaha-shs-10/"/>
    <updated>2020-02-04T18:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>https://joshcrain.io/notes/2020/yamaha-shs-10/</id>
    <content type="html"><p><span class="dropcap">B</span>ack in 2006, I stumbled upon a website called <a href="http://lifeinvector.com/">Life In Vector</a>. At the time I was still learning what Illustrator could do, the work was eye-opening. I followed the <a href="http://lifeinvector.com/downloads/">gradient mesh tutorial</a> for a red pepper (I cannot believe this is still online) and learned a lot about working more effectively with layers and gradients.</p>
<figure>
    <img src="https://joshcrain.io/images/keytar/yamaha-shs-10.png" alt="Yamaha SHS-10 Keytar">
    <figcaption>Yamaha SHS-10 rendered in Adobe Illustrator.</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Everything rendered this way seemed to have a plastic quality so I began to look for something that <em>was</em> plastic. At the time I played the keytar in a band called Dr. Mike (<a href="https://www.amazon.com/Mighty-Love-Dr-Mike/dp/B000FSMMNK/">Amazon</a>,  <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/a-mighty-love/97175026">iTunes</a>). The SHS-10 was perfect. I spent the next several weeks over lunch breaks working on it. I still see this image in searches for the Yamaha SHS-10, even though it’s been at least ten years since I last published it online.</p>
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Forsaken</title>
    <link href="https://joshcrain.io/notes/2020/forsaken/"/>
    <updated>2019-07-17T19:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://joshcrain.io/notes/2020/forsaken/</id>
    <content type="html"><p>Forsaken places.</p>
<figure>
    <img src="https://joshcrain.io/images/forsaken/768/forsaken-0.jpg">
    <figcaption>Running horses on the Redding road. </figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <img src="https://joshcrain.io/images/forsaken/768/forsaken-1.jpg">
    <figcaption>House on Cemetery Hill.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <img src="https://joshcrain.io/images/forsaken/768/forsaken-2.jpg">
    <figcaption>Blockton Sculptures. </figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <img src="https://joshcrain.io/images/forsaken/768/forsaken-3.jpg">
    <figcaption>Trailer on Cemetery Hill.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <img src="https://joshcrain.io/images/forsaken/768/forsaken-4.jpg">
    <figcaption>House on Cemetery Hill.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <img src="https://joshcrain.io/images/forsaken/768/forsaken-5.jpg">
    <figcaption>House south of Zearing.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <img src="https://joshcrain.io/images/forsaken/768/forsaken-6.jpg">
    <figcaption>House south of Zearing.</figcaption>
</figure>
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Arizona &amp;amp; Utah</title>
    <link href="https://joshcrain.io/notes/2020/arizona-and-utah/"/>
    <updated>2019-07-17T19:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://joshcrain.io/notes/2020/arizona-and-utah/</id>
    <content type="html"><figure class="pull--both">
    <img src="https://joshcrain.io/images/arizona-utah/1024/montezuma-1.jpeg" alt="Montezuma Castle">
<figcaption>
Montezuma Castle National Monument, Arizona.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="pull--both">
    <img src="https://joshcrain.io/images/arizona-utah/1024/bryce-canyon-1.jpeg" alt="Bryce Canyon">
<figcaption>Bryce Canyon National Park, Utah.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <img src="https://joshcrain.io/images/arizona-utah/768/bryce-canyon-2.jpeg" alt="Bryce Canyon">
<figcaption>Bryce Canyon National Park, Utah.</figcaption>
</figure> 
<figure>
    <img src="https://joshcrain.io/images/arizona-utah/768/bryce-canyon-3.jpeg" alt="Bryce Canyon">
    <figcaption>Bryce Canyon National Park, Utah.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="pull--both">
        <img src="https://joshcrain.io/images/arizona-utah/1024/bryce-canyon-4.jpeg" alt="Bryce Canyon">
    <figcaption>Natural Bridge. Bryce Canyon National Park, Utah. </figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="pull--both">
    <img src="https://joshcrain.io/images/arizona-utah/1024/bryce-canyon-5.jpeg" alt="Bryce Canyon">
    <figcaption>Bryce Canyon National Park, Utah. </figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <img src="https://joshcrain.io/images/arizona-utah/768/bryce-canyon-7.jpeg" alt="Bryce Canyon">
    <figcaption>Bryce Canyon National Park, Utah.</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <img src="https://joshcrain.io/images/arizona-utah/1024/grand-canyon-1.jpeg" alt="Grand Canyon">
    <figcaption>Grand Canyon National Park, Arizona. </figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="pull--both">
    <img src="https://joshcrain.io/images/arizona-utah/1024/grand-canyon-2.jpeg" alt="Grand Canyon">
    <figcaption> Inner Canyon. Grand Canyon National Park, Arizona. </figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="pull--both">
    <img src="https://joshcrain.io/images/arizona-utah/1024/paria-ut-1.jpeg" alt="Paria">
    <figcaption>Banded hills of the Chinle Formation, near the Paria movie set. Grand Staircase-Escalante National Monument, Utah. </figcaption>
</figure>
<div class="text_center">There are more photos from this trip on <a href="https://flickr.com/photos/joshuacrain/albums/72157670159343188" rel="noopener">Flickr</a>!</div>
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>A Run</title>
    <link href="https://joshcrain.io/notes/2019/a-run/"/>
    <updated>2019-05-28T19:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://joshcrain.io/notes/2019/a-run/</id>
    <content type="html"><p><span class="dropcap">T</span>hat was the night I planned to run six but instead ended up on a gravel road in the middle of a twelve-mile loop. There was enough light to see, even beyond the glow of the city lights, because the moon was full and the night was clear. The night sky was black as ink, and the moon was bright against it. I noticed my shadow over my right shoulder, clear against the soft glow of the light blue limestone. It looked so much different than during the day.</p>
<p>For a while, I only listened to the rocks under my feet and my steady breaths. I began to wonder why I’d changed my mind. Why didn’t I run what I’d planned? If you’d asked me earlier in the day I’m sure I would have given you a long list of reasons not to. We put in a lot of miles the week before, and besides it was late. As a runner, you always think about how the run fits into the completed and upcoming mileage. In the morning, when your body aches and creaks you curse your poor judgment from the day before. Still, there is something about running at night that’s different than the day. Something, I’m sure I’ll forget by morning.</p>
<figure>
    <img src="https://joshcrain.io/images/a-day-in-the-life-video-still_3821176372_o.jpg" alt="A day in the life. Video still.">
    <figcaption>A Day In The Life. Senior BFA project. Video still.</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>I felt much different than the day before. This was the first run in a long time to feel this way. It was an intoxicating feeling, the “runner’s high” everyone talks about. I left the house an hour or so before, and it took a moment to remember what had prompted me to run when I did. I thought hard to recall the exact words, but couldn’t. I was frustrated, my head burned and my mind raced. I laced up my shoes and started my watch on the way out the front door. It happened earlier that week too, maybe Tuesday, but it was hard to remember. My memory faded and I again focused on my shadow. I was only a few feet from the ditch and my outline became a bit more obscure against the tall grass.</p>
<p>I looked at my watch and figured my split for the second half seemed a little faster. I was only about a quarter mile from town, so the lights began to overtake the night sky. The only thing I heard between my breaths were my near silent feet on the black grass next to the sidewalk. The sky wasn’t as dark as a few moments before, the moon nearly extinguished by the amber street lights. As I approached each light my shadow caught me from behind and then lengthened out in front of my feet as I passed. I watched my shadow for a while and then noticed the pace the ground traveled under my feet. I had started to feel tired a couple miles back, but had I quickened the pace? I looked at my watch. I was faster—by a couple minutes.</p>
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>140 miles from the Camp Fire</title>
    <link href="https://joshcrain.io/notes/2020/the-camp-fire/"/>
    <updated>2018-11-21T18:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>https://joshcrain.io/notes/2020/the-camp-fire/</id>
    <content type="html"><p class="lead">The Camp Fire was the deadliest and most destructive wildfire in California history. The fire began on November 8, 2018&mdash;the day we arrived.</p>
<figure>
    <img src="https://joshcrain.io/images/camp-fire/768/muir-woods.jpg">
    <figcaption>Muir Woods. November 8, 2018</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <img src="https://joshcrain.io/images/camp-fire/768/camp-fire-1.jpg">
    <figcaption>North of Muir Woods on California State Route 1. November 8, 2018</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <img src="https://joshcrain.io/images/camp-fire/768/camp-fire-3.jpg">
    <figcaption>Bodega Head, Bodega Bay. November 9, 2018</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>We parked the car near a marked trail and traced a few narrow paths across Bodega Head searching for a view. In the distance the bay and horizon were one, grounded only by the sea stacks. Closer now to the the ocean the air moved more freely, the briny smells of beach below stifled by the static haze. We retraced our steps and continued south until we reached a marker for Shell Beach. Crooked wooden steps descended down the bluff.</p>
<figure>
    <img src="https://joshcrain.io/images/camp-fire/768/camp-fire-2.jpg">
    <figcaption>Shell Beach, Bodega Bay. November 9, 2018</figcaption>
</figure>
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>